<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle of a Catholicke young gentleman, (being for his religion imprisoned.) To his father a Protestant Who commaunded him to set downe in writing, what were the motiues that induced him to become a Catholicke.</title>
            <author>N. N., fl. 1614.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68490</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18330</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114781</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850004</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850004</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15185</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68490)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15185)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1270:29, 1525:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle of a Catholicke young gentleman, (being for his religion imprisoned.) To his father a Protestant Who commaunded him to set downe in writing, what were the motiues that induced him to become a Catholicke.</title>
                  <author>N. N., fl. 1614.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed with licence. [i.e. printed by the English Secret Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Doway [i.e. printed secretly in England] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>End of text on p. 40 dated: 15. day of August, being the 46. th weeke of my imprisonment, 1614.</note>
                  <note>Actual suggested imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 10431.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 10431 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1270 and at reel 1525 (both are Bodleian copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conversion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15185:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15185:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EPISTLE OF A CATHOLICKE YOVNG GENTLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAN, (Being for his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on impriſoned.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To his Father a Proteſtant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who commaunded him to ſet downe in Writing, what were the motiues that induced him to become a <hi>Catholicke.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Noli exubeſcere teſtimonium Domini no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> me vinctum euis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Be not aſhamed of the teſtimony of our Lord, nor of mee his Priſoner.</p>
               <bibl>1. <hi>Timoth. Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>DOWAY. Printed with Licence. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15185:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15185:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>I No ſooner had peruſed this ſhort Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, then I had an earneſt deſire it might bee Publiſhed in Print, as well for that I obſerued the groundes which this young Gentleman had layde downe to his Father to bee both ſncſinct and Learned! as alſo for that I am well perſwaded the promulgation thereof, would (God aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting) giue much good ſatisfaction to any iudicious Reader, and for that I neuer had any acquaintance with the Author, I mooued ſecretly a very Friend of mine (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate with him) to perſwade him (if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) to put it to the Preſſe: which motion hee not onely abſolutely refuſed, but was alſo infinitely diſpleaſed with the Moouer, wherefore to preuent (what in him lay) the printing and publiſhing of the ſaid Epiſtle, he not onely refuſed vtterly to giue Coppies thereof, but alſo ecclipſed it from the view of all men. But the Father more prodigall then the Sonne himſelfe, carried the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall continually about him, making no dainty at all to ſhew it in St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> the Pawne, <hi>Youngs</hi> Ordinary in Corne-hill, and in many other places at his pleaſure, he making it his common Table-diſcourſe <pb facs="tcp:15185:3"/> in Tauernes and Ordinaries: by which meanes I obtained a Coppy, which (though long after) I ſent ouer Seas to a Friend, deſiring him to cauſe it to bee Printed. Reade it through with good attention, and if thou reape any profite thereby; forget not to render due thankes to GOD, and then in thy Prayers remember both the Author and the Publiſher.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15185:3"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL HIS VERY LOVING Father <hi>N. N.</hi> Eſquire, giue theſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NVmberleſſe (I may truely ſay) haue bin the attempts I haue made in writing vnto you, and as many in number were the obſtacles which haue oppoſed my ſaid attempts: The effects of ſome of them are to this houre to be ſeene (if I liſt to produce them to the quantity, And I doe keepe me within compaſſe) of at the leaſt 24. ſheetes of Paper, which I intended to your good ſelfe, which by that time they could be finiſhed, I had motiues exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatory to call them backe, and not by any meanes to ſend them. But yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, to exempt my ſelfe from hauing any imputation of diſobedience wherewith to be taxed, I haue now at the laſt (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming more upon your Fatherly chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then any other merite in my ſelfe) beene bolde, to preſent vnto you theſe few lines, wherein I haue deliuered
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15185:4"/> briefly, that which I had heretofore han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled more at large; in the paſſages wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I haue heere ſet you downe moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuouſly, according to your moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant requeſt, from whence haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the motiues, which cauſed me to abiure the Religion in practice amongſt Proteſtants, and to aſſume the true, holy, and neuer erring Catholike and Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxall Faith, and thereunto to adhere: Neither doe I herein goe about to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you, but onely to keepe corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence with your deſire and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, being that I finde my ſelfe bound in all Conſcience, to performe ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, which you ſhall require at my hands, ſuppoſing them to be no way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating to Gods honour, or to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity of my particular ſelfe, in making imminent perill of my ſoules ſhipwrack, where in a caſe of ſuch a nature I am not lyable.</p>
            <p>I am therefore an humble ſuter vnto you (good Sir) in that you would bee pleaſed ſo farre to fauour me, as to daine with alacrity the peruſe of theſe fewe lines, and that with ſerious mature iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and then I hope you will not bee ſo ſtrict in cenſuring mee for my aſſumed <pb n="3" facs="tcp:15185:4"/> Religion, nor yet in blaming me for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoing with all patience and chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, this long &amp; auſtere time of durance: but you will rather (I hope) commiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate my eſtate, which howſoeuer to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers it might appeare irkſome and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable, to mee (I giue God moſt humble thankes) it is a greater conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation then any temporall (conſidering for whoſe ſake it is) guerdon or reſpect the whole world is able to affoord me. And the conſideration hereof, hath beene of that efficacy and power with mee, as that I am at all times readily prepared, with no leſſe willingneſſe, to vndergoe, not onely Impriſonment, in the moſt auſtere manner may bee ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, but alſo in the ſeruice of ſo noble a Maſter, torture, ſtripes, gyues, yea the moſt prodigious and dolorous death the heart and capacity of man is able to inuent; For I know well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, that whatſoeuer I doe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe in this behalfe, I doe in it reſtore him but his owne, and am neuer able to come out of debt, albeit I had as many liues to looſe, as I haue in this vile &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Carkaſſe of mine, drops of blood to ſhed; neither ſhall I herein diſſent <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15185:5"/> from that holy and reuerend Doctor and Piller of Gods Church Saint <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> who for his ſweete and delicate ſtile, is intituled <hi>Mellifluus,</hi> who ſaith thus; <hi>Si totum me debeo pro me facto, quid addam iam pro me refecto:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sermo de di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligendo Deo.</note> 
               <hi>nec e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim faceli refectus quam factus. In primo opere me mihi dedit, in ſecundo ſe, &amp; vbi ſe dedit me mihi reddidit: Datus ergo &amp; redditus, me pro me debeo, &amp; bis debeo; ſed quid Domino pro ſe retribuam, nam et ſi me millies rependere poſſem, quid ſum ad Dominum meum?</hi> That is; <hi>If I owe my ſelfe wholly for my firſt making, what can I adde more for my redeeming, eſpecially ſeeing I was not ſo eaſily Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as I was made. In the firſt worke hee gaue me my ſelfe, in the ſecond himſelfe, and when hee gaue mee himſelfe, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored vnto mee my ſelfe, Therefore thus giuen and reſtored, I owe my ſelfe for my ſelfe, and I owe my ſelfe twice.</hi> But now what I am able to repay my Lord for himſelfe, for although I were able to repay my ſelfe a thouſand times, what am I in compariſon of my Lord? which beeing ſo, what then can bee the feare why I ſhould not giue my ſelfe freely to my Creator? Sithence he hath in <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15185:5"/> me a double intereſt, to wit, aſwell in reſpect of my Creation, as of my Redemption, the leaſt of which two workes being vnualuable.</p>
            <p>The ſerious conſiderations hereof (good Sir) haue wrought in me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utterable effects, and ſuch as haue cauſed mee hereby to ſettle ſo irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable an affection vpon the moſt Bleſſed Trinity, in regard of my Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and Redemption, as enforceth me with no ſmall vehemency, to cry out with the Kingly Prophet, ſaying; <hi>Quid retribuam Domino,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 115.</note> 
               <hi>pro omnibus quae retribuit mihi? What ſhall I repay our Lord for all thinges which he hath giuen vnto me:</hi> certainly when I haue done what I haue beene able, I am, <hi>Seruus inutilis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 17.</note> 
               <hi>au vnprofitable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant,</hi> and <hi>Indignus vocari filius euis, vnworthy to be called his Sonne.</hi> The conſideration whereof, was long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it came into my minde, for that I muſt not deny, but that I ſpent much time in a moſt exorbitant courſe of life, which I doe now from my heart repent, and deſire that Gods grace may neuer more depart from me, ſo as I may for euer hereafter liue, as an <pb n="6" facs="tcp:15185:6"/> obedient, &amp; not as a rebellious Child, hauing ſo deare, louing, and tender, and a Father, who ſaith daily vnto me:

<note place="margin">Pſal. 102.</note>
               <hi>Qui propitiatur omnibus iniquitatibus tuis, &amp; qui ſanat omnes imfirmitates tuas, quired mi de interitu vtam tuam, qui coronat te in miſerecordia, &amp; miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationibus, qui replet in bonis deſidere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um tuum, &amp;c.</hi> That is, <hi>Who is mercifull to all thy iniquities, and who cureth all thy infirmities, who redeemed thy life from Death, who Crowneth thee in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and compaſſions, who repleniſheth thy deſire in good thinges, &amp;c.</hi> The remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of theſe thus skirmiſhing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me, haue bin impregnable, and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtable motiues, which preſſed mee to determine vppon a more morrall worme, wherby to meaſure the ſquare of my life: and theſe determinations made me thinke vpon Religion, and Religion begat Deuotion, and Deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on brought with it a firme Reſolution, which Reſolution, being aſſiſted by Almighty Gods grace, hath wonne me to ſtand againſt all terrors &amp; temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and which haue occaſioned me to addreſſe theſe Lines vnto you, whereby I doe intend to giue you a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15185:6"/> taſte, from what motiues and grounds I doe build my Faith; which if you be able to refell, I ſhall be very willing to belieue, that a man may be ſaued in the Proteſtants Church, which neither Scriptures, Fathers, Counſels, or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was euer able to make me vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Hauing therefore thus miſpent my time, and <hi>Quaſi ſeruus nequam, like to an euill ſeruant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Math.
18.</note> conſumed my youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger yeares, yea the prime of my daies, in vanity and irregularity, It hath pleaſed Almighty God at the length to touch my heart with a due conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of my mortality, and with ſome care of eternity; Inſomuch as the more I ſeriouſly obſerued the frailty, and abſurdity of the one, the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly I affected the loue, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of the other, that finally I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to hunt after it, albeit the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages and difficulties of my life were neuer ſo many, reſting now well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, That, <hi>Nil prodeſt homini ſi v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſum mundum lucreter, animae vero ſuae detrimentum patiatur. It auaileth nothing to gaine the whole world, if a man make ſhipwracke of his owne Soule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibidem 16.</note> 
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15185:7"/> which to ſaue hereafter, we are taught to ſaue heere; That is, to expoſe it to all afflictions &amp; contradictions, which the world, the Diuell, or our owne ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall appetite doe continually ſtirre vp againſt vs, For <hi>much better it is for a man to enter into life euerlaſting lame, blinde, or diſmembred, then to be plunged into the bottomleſſe Pet of inquenchable ſulphurous Hell, with all our ſences and members.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibidem 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Theſe therefore, and the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations incouraged me ſincerely to ſeeke after Truth, ſwayed neither with feare nor fauour, but onely guided with that vnmouing Pole, whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence had touched my heart, like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another Loadſtone, that howſoeuer theſe mortall waues toſſed my vnſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy barke, the proofe of my affections euer bent that way, I could very well haue contented my ſelfe to follow my appetite ſtill But <hi>durum eſt contra ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulum calcitrare, It is hard ſtriuing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Almighty God, and dangerous to harden our hearts againſt his calles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 9.</note> Wherefore, I yeeld my ſelfe, ſaying; <hi>Domine quid me vis facere? What O Lord is thy pleaſure I ſhall doe?</hi> And <pb n="9" facs="tcp:15185:7"/> herewith me thought, I heard this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable anſwer, viz. <hi>Dicitur tibi quid te oporteat facere, Thou muſt be taught what thou muſt doe:</hi> and taught I muſt be, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence the knowledge I ſought after, was aboue humane reach to comprehend and finde; For theſe tidings came out of Heauen, &amp;
<hi>Vnigenitus qui eſt in ſuum Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris ipſe enarrabit, The onely begotten Son who is in the boſome of the Father, hee will deliuer them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.</note> and they onely can haue them,
<note place="margin">S. Math. 11.</note>
               <hi>Cui filius voluerit reuelare, to whom it ſhall pleaſe the Sonne to reueale it. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis autem reuelauit Deus pro ſpiritum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, Spiritus enim omnia ſcrutatur, etiam profunda Dei. But vnto vs hath God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed it by his Spirit, for, the Spirit tryeth all thinges, yea, the profundities of God</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor.
2.</note> Shewing, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this knowledge could come from none other but only fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him alone.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thus then being deſirous of this knowledge, and perceiuing it not to be humane, but Diuine, <hi>Quemadmodum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderat ceruus ad fontes aquarum, Looke how the heart haſteth to the Fountaines of water.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 41.</note> Euen ſo earneſtly did I thirſt after ſome certaine rule, guidance, or directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereby to be led or conducted, by which meanes I might attaine vnto what <pb n="10" facs="tcp:15185:8"/> ſoeuer humane induſtry could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire, and this needeth no further proofe, as being in it ſelfe manifeſt, and by the joint and mutuall conſent aſwell of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks as of Proteſtants receiued. But of this Doctrine I collected further, that this rule or direction we ſpeake of, muſt containe two ſeueral properties, to make it auaileable for the end, for which it is required: Firſt it muſt be plaine, eaſie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently open or manifeſt to all, &amp; the reaſon good, for it muſt be a direction as well to the wiſe, as to the ſimple, to the Learned, as to the ignorant, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence all theſe muſt (before they can be ſaued) be inſtructed in this ſupernaturall Science, without which can be no acceſſe to grace,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note> entrance into Heauen, or poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to pleaſe that Diuine Maieſty, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the holy Apoſtle teacheth vs, and therefore the Prophet foretelleth of this way, ſaying:
<note place="margin">Eſay 35.</note>
               <hi>Et erit ibi ſemita &amp; via, &amp; via ſancta vocabitur, &amp;c.</hi> And conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>Haec erit vobis directa via, ita vt ſtulti non errent per eam.</hi> That is, <hi>And there ſhall be in that place a path, and a way, that ſhall be your direct way, ſo that fooles ſhall not erre in it.</hi> The ſecond pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of this rule is, that it muſt be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15185:8"/> and infallible, and the reaſon is, for that the knowlege of our Faith depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereupon, muſt be certaine, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, ſo as it may be no more ſubiect to error then truth it ſelfe is to falſhood; the credit thereof muſt be greater then of an Angell of Heauen.
<note place="margin">Gal. 1.</note>
               <hi>Licet nos</hi> (ſaith St.
<hi>Paul) aut Angelus de Coelo, euangelizet preterquam quod euangelizauimus vobis, anathema ſit. If our ſelues, or an Angell from Heauen, ſhall Euangelize or Preach to you otherwiſe then wee haue Preached, accurſed let him be.</hi> For if our Faith might be ſubiect to rrror, then did it not rely vpon the truth of God, and then it were no diuine Faith. Againe, if in that Faith by which we are ſaued we might be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to falſhood,<note place="margin">See William Perkins, pro. de fide n. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> then by falſhood we might be ſaued, and by vntruth attaine to truth, which parradoxe is both blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous hnd ridiculous. Authorities of holy Scriptures, conſent of venerable antiquity, and the vnanimous approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the vniuerſall Church, I could produce for the truth of theſe properties; but I holde them needleſſe for that in themſelues they doe appeare moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous, and by no Proteſtants which I can reade of, are they denyed, as by all <pb n="12" facs="tcp:15185:9"/> Catholicks is confeſſed. I hauing thus farre waded, at the length I began to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, where this rule and direction is to be found, that by conſent therof, I might be conuayed to that knowledge which ſo much importeth me, and therefore I doe here inquire of the Proteſtant, and he telleth me readily, that true it is, ſuch a rule muſt guide all Chriſtians, and is to be found in their Church, contained in their Bible, and by them tearmed the word of the Lord, and diuine Scriptures; this they ſay is eaſie, plaine, and an infallible direction to all who ſeeke after Heauen, and heauenly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p n="5">5 But heere I am intangled with ſo many difficulties, ſo that I am rather puſled, clouded, and encombred, then any way freed, cleared, or aſcertained of any truth. Firſt, how can it appeare vnto mee that I may be aſſured, that this Booke is the word of God, and of that continuance and authority where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I ſpeake: Wee ſee many workes beare Saint
<hi>Auguſtines</hi> name, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of other Fathers, which Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants ſtoutly deny to bee theirs; yet <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15185:9"/> not ſo auncient as their Booke of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſt be, if it be true Scripture in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; Heere I inquire ſo certaine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth, that in it ſelfe it be plaine for all men to perceiue it, and ſo certaine, that it ſhould be impoſſible how it could be otherwiſe, elſe (as I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid) it cannot guide or warrantiſe Diuine and infallible Faith. But I haue euer found Proteſtants ſo extreamely puſled in this point, that they know not how to extricate themſelues, their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers were ſo weake, different, diſjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and vncertaine, that at the laſt they haue no refuge, but to depend vpon the tradition of the Roman Church, from whence they haue their Scriptures; yea, and thoſe traditions alſo they muſt grant to be of infallible truth and Faith, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe their Scriptures will not carry cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite ſufficient whereupon to build an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Faith, and yet if they graunt this, they ſuffocate and choake their owne cauſe in many eſſentiall, and important points of difference twixt them and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, ſo as this Rule ought to be cleare, eaſie, and infallible, is no ſooner looked vpon, but it is preſently loſt in ambiguities, doubts, and vncertainties.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:15185:10"/>6 And admit that they were able in the grounds of their Doctrine to produce any one infallible, plaine, &amp; certaine rule, aſſuring me that the Booke they ſhew me, is the word of God, or written by ſuch ſacred Authors as they tell of, which they are neuer able to doe;<note place="margin">
                  <p>See <hi>Iohn Cal in</hi> Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſat. in no: teſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Zanch.</hi> lib. de Sanctis fol. 412. tom. 2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Beza</hi> in reſp. ad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fen. Caſt.</p>
                  <p>Ite <hi>Beza</hi> in praefat. no. teſt. 1556.</p>
                  <p>Car. moli. in tranſla. no. ceſt. par. 11. fol. 110.</p>
                  <p>Ite parte 64. 65. 66. 74. 99.</p>
                  <p>See confe. at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court pag. 46.</p>
               </note> yet are they preſently encumbred with another diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, which maketh all vncertaine, which is contained in it: For in former times of a great part of this volume, the Greeke tranſlations were many, the Latine more, of late ſince <hi>Luther</hi> began, from him, his complices, and Of-ſpring, the tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons haue bin diuers and ſo different, that one condemneth another to Hell, for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting, falſifying, and abuſing of holy Scriptures; yea
<hi>Luther</hi> himſelfe differeth in aboue 30. places (as I can eaſily ſhew) from himſelfe, in ſeuerall tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of St. <hi>Mathewes</hi> Goſpell, out of theſe into Engliſh, we haue at the leaſt 7. or eight ſeuarall verſions, of all which his Maieſty pronounceth there is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a good, and the <hi>Geneua</hi> be the worſt of all.</p>
            <p>Heere I would ſee how the ignorant or learned, (amid ſuch diuerſity of opinions in men of knowledge in all ſacred langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15185:10"/> can with aſſurance and certainty, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the true Tranſlations from the falſe, that it be impoſſible to erre herein, for if in this caſe there can be no infallible rule, and direction plaine and eaſie, for all men to vnderſtand, (as I haue before deliuered) it is impoſſible that any man can be able to ſettle an infallible, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer erring Faith, vpon any thing contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in it, when as he is not certaine what is the true word of God, and what by Ignorance, Error, or wilfulnes is thruſt in by humaine inuention, and ſubiect to falſhood.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Heere not onely the Ignorant is ſo intangled, with the Brackes and Toyles of vncertainty, and inſtability, ſo as he knoweth not which way to get out, yea findeth impoſſibility by his owne indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry euer whileſt he ſhall liue to cleare himſelfe: But the Learned alſo are no leſſe clouded with endleſſe variety, and difference among ſuch as are no leſſe (yea more) learned then themſelues, hauing no reaſon whereupon to relye their owne Iudgements before others, and bee ſo aſſured thereof, as that it is impoſſible they ſhould be deceiued, and conſequently, to frame an Article <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15185:11"/> of Diuine Faith vpon the aſſurance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. So as out of this head, this rule of onely Scriptures, hath loſt not onely cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainety, but perſpicuity alſo, both which are very much behoofefull in the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof I ſpeake.</p>
            <p n="8">8 And heere in my vnderſtanding it cannot be anſwered, as in the Proeme of the new Bible,<note place="margin">See <hi>Calu.</hi> vbi ſupra.</note> thoſe Tranſlations ſay, to wit, that this diuerſity is not in matters appertaining vnto Faith,<note place="margin">Ioſias Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerus
<hi>in vita</hi> Bullinger.</note> but in other pointes of leſſe conſequence. Firſt, that is not true, as by the inuectiues ſome of the Tranſlations make againſt the reſt doth appeare. Againe, in moſt pointes of Controuerſies betwixt them and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, they tranſlate places concerning thoſe points, differently from the olde Latine receiued aboue 1000. yeares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe in Gods Church, onely in fauour of their owne heriſies and opinions, being matters of Faith; As for example, they tranſlate for Prieſts, Elders; for Idols, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, &amp;c. I ſay yet further, that in ſo much as all matters there, is the true Word of God, and I partly finde that ſome part thereof is miſtranſlated, and that is proued by the diuerſities of thoſe Tranſlations, diſſonant each to other;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15185:11"/> Therefore cannot all bee true: in regard hereof (I ſay) I muſt require a ſure, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and infallible Rule, by the which it may remaine vndoubted, that thoſe errors or miſtakings were in matters of Faith, as well as leſſe matters, ſithence I could neuer heare of any Warranty out of Heauen, aſſuring theſe tranſlations in matters of Faith, more than in ſmaller matters.</p>
            <p n="9">9 But admit againe, that Proteſtants had ſome ſure &amp; infallible rule, or meanes to aſcertaine vs that this which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or any of theſe, is the ſincere tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of Gods word, yet are we as deeply incombred as euer, for inſomuch as Gods word conſiſteth not in bare characters or ſillables, but in the ſpirit and meaning of that writing, where (I pray) is that plaine and infallible Rule, which Proteſtants can aſſigne, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct whereof who ſo followeth, cannot poſſibly erre in the true meaning of holy Scripture. For without this all the reſt is nothing auaileable to ſuſtaine an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Faith, and an error or miſtaking herein, is ſo pernicious and damnable, that whoſoeuer is poſſeſſed therewith, cannot poſſibly enter Heauen.
<hi>Qui non <pb n="18" facs="tcp:15185:12"/>
                  <note place="margin">St. Ioh. 3.</note>credit iam iudicatus eſt, who beleeueth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right is already iudged.</hi> And
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note>
               <hi>ſine fide impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibile eſt placere Deo, without Faith it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to pleaſe God:</hi> And our Faith is not grounded vpon letters, Characters, or ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lables, but of the ſignification &amp; true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the holy Ghoſt vttered in them.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Heere againe I finde Proteſtants ſo masked, or hoodwinckt, that they know not which way to take, or what to ſay, as may eaſily appeare by the poore ſhifts they are put vnto, when in this matter they are by Catholickes called to accompt. And firſt it is a vſuall refuge of theirs to ſay, that the Scripture is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and plaine of it ſelfe, to be vnderſtood of euery one without difficulty or am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguity: But this is ſo apparantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trowlde, with the forme and matter of Scripture, and euery mans particuler ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that it plainely diſcouereth the weakenes and inſufficiency thereof. As for the forme &amp; ſtile it is repleate with Maieſty and depth, it containeth many Hebraiciſmes and Greciſmes, which the ignorant and vnlearned doe not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, yea, &amp; many times the moſt Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned doe make doubt &amp; differ about, for that it doth containe ſo profound matter <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15185:12"/> aboue ordinary capacity. As the Trinity and Vnity in God, the Incarnation, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and Aſcention of Chriſt our moſt B. Sauiour, together with his Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hood, and preſence in the moſt Bleſſed Euchariſt, with the like, which doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolue great &amp; hidden miſteries, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found difficulties, containing many ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming contradictions, which to reconcile great Clerks &amp; holy Fathers, haue much trauailed, writing whole Bookes &amp; large tomes therof, againſt
<hi>Iulia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> the Apoſtata, &amp; other enemies of Chriſtianity.
<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> conf. cap.
<hi>5.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Iuſtitui animam</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine) intendere in Scripturas ſacras, &amp;c. I intended to bend my minde to holy Scriptures to ſee the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of them, and beholde, I ſee a thing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to the proude, not open to Children, but in gate lowly, in effect lofty, and couered with myſteries, neither was I ſuch as I could enter into it, or bowe my necke to the entrance of it,</hi> So he. Thus did this holy Father and great Doctor finde the holy Scriptures, which Proteſtants make ſo eaſie &amp; plaine, and thus doth euery mans experience teach, not only in the endles diuerſity of expoſitions, betweene Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks &amp; Sectaries, but eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Sectaries themſelues, Proteſtants
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15185:13"/> with Proteſtants, who haue filled the world with their ianglings, and giuen te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony that they ſpeake againſt their Conſciences, and knowledge, when they ſay that the Scriptures are eaſie for euery one to vnderſtand, elſe why ſhould they ſpend ſo much time in making ſo many Expoſitions, and Commentaries, and in filling Bookes, to make that vnderſtood, which euery man with ſo much eaſe doth conceiue: or why ſhould they after all their Commentaries, leaue all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies of Scriptures more ambiguous then before, yea in ſtead of clearing all doubts, beget infinite new controuerſies before vnheard of.</p>
            <p n="11">11 And from hence doth appeare, how poore and weake an Anſwer that other is which (many brought into ſtraights) flie vnto, ſaying that Scriptures are made plaine by conferring one place with another; for this both Catholickes and their oppoſites, with all diligence doe affirme; yet agree neuer the more by this: neither are they conuinced of one Truth: St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1. Abacuc. 2. Gal. 3. Heb. 10. Act.
15.</note>
               <hi>Iuſtus ex fide viuit,</hi> The <hi>Iuſt man liueth by his Faith;</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Fide purificans corda hominum,</hi> God <hi>by Faith purifying the hearts of men.</hi> 
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:15185:13"/> And St.
<hi>Iames</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">St. Iam. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Sicut corpus ſine Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritu mortuum eſt, ita &amp; fides ſine operibus mortua eſt,</hi> like <hi>as the body without the Spirit is dead, euen ſo alſo Faith without workes is dead and nothing auaileable.</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants explicate St. <hi>Iames</hi> by St. <hi>Paul:</hi> but Catholicks explaine St.
<hi>Paul</hi> by St. <hi>Iames;</hi> This diuerſity hath wel nigh co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued
100. yeares, toſſed &amp; diſcuſſed with all diligence, yet not to this day agreed vpon between them; &amp; ſo the like in all other points of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſies we doe find.</p>
            <p n="12">12 Moreouer I demaund whether af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conference of places, ſuch as doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly finde Truth thereby, that it be impoſſible hauing ſo done to be decci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; if you ſay they doe, then you will be controwled by dayly experience, as well in Proteſtants as in Catholicks, who after all differ as before; which could not be, if by this meanes they did infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly finde the Truth, For
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note>
               <hi>that is but one, as God is one, and Faith one:</hi> But if you graunt all that conference of places, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the true meaning of holy Scriptures, and conſequently cannot ſerue for the purpoſe we treate of.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Others confeſſe, that conference of places cannot be ſufficient in this caſe, <pb n="22" facs="tcp:15185:14"/> but avow that Almighty God will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hart of euery one in particular that ſeeketh the knowledge of his Truth. But this ſeemeth vnto me the moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, deſperate, and vnlikely ſhift of all vnlikelihoods: for, (as I haue ſaid) not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this priuate Spirit, we ſee the diuerſity dayly encreaſed, rather then any way diminiſhed, which could not be if God particularly and infallibly guided euery one that heartily deſired the truth: then muſt you ſhew a meane how euery one ſhall know or be infallibly aſſured that this priuate expoſition is true; and all contrary to it falſe; and then muſt he ſhew how he commeth by that ſpeciall guift, denyed to all that differ from him, or how we can be aſſured therof, or how is this rule generall to all, which ſo many ſo earneſtly trauailing for truth ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet attaine not vnto: this therefore ſo repugnant to euery mans reaſon &amp; expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, ſeemeth only a rendeuous which men are driuen to retire vnto, hauing no better to ſuccor or help themſelues with; for mine owne part thus much I ſay and know, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in ſincere deſire of truth I yeeld to none, I know it, the life of my ſoule, I preferre before all worldly treaſures, <pb n="23" facs="tcp:15185:14"/> and as I rancke not my ſelfe among the Learned, ſo am I not the moſt vnlearned among the ignorant and vnlearned: yet when I peruſe the holy Scriptures, I doe find them ſo deep, ſo profound, &amp; ſo dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficill, that I can aſſure my ſelfe of nothing, which by mine owne induſtry I am able to attaine vnto, much leſſe find it ſo eaſie and plaine as to haue infallible aſſurance of what I conceiue; wherefore I muſt of neceſſity ſeeke that aſſurance elſe where, and take direction fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſurer knowledge then mine owne, or any my ſelfe can ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of holy Scriptures: otherwiſe I ſhall faſhion &amp; molde out a very feeble and fickle Faith, &amp; voide of all certainty. <hi>Putaſne intelligis quae legis?</hi> (ſaith St.
<hi>Philip</hi> to the Eunuch)
<note place="margin">Act. 8.</note>
               <hi>Thinkeſt thou that thou vnderſtandeſt what thou readeſt?</hi> hauing the olde Teſtament in his hands. <hi>Quomodo poſſum ſi non aliquis oſtenderit mihi? How can I</hi> (ſaith the Eunuch)
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> Apoc 2.5.</note>
               <hi>vnleſſe ſome body ſhall ſhew me? Ego</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Hierome) nec ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctior ſum hoc Eunucho, nec ſtudioſior, &amp;c. I am not holyer nor better ſtudyed then this Eunuch,</hi> and concludeth in theſe wordes. Theſe things I haue briefly mentioned, to the end you may vnderſtand y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not enter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Scriptures without a guide, <pb n="24" facs="tcp:15185:15"/> and one who ſhall ſhew thee the way.</p>
            <p>This I finding to be moſt true, by all reaſon and experience in my ſelfe, and diligent obſeruation in others, I bent my labours and ſtudy to finde out this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py guide, which infallibly and without danger of erring, would inſtruct me with the true meaning of holy Scriptures. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing plainly therefore that the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants rule of Scriptures, could not ſerue for this purpoſe, I begin to examine what aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce Catholicks had for their beliefe or expoſitions, whereupon they relyed.</p>
            <p n="14">14 They confeſſe a plaine, eaſie and infallible rule, muſt guide in matters of Faith: they ſay moreouer that cannot be any dead or dumbe writing, be it neuer ſo Sacred: for nothing can be written ſo plaine but in many clawſes or paſſages it will beare ſeuerall conſtructions; where ſeuerall conſtructions are, there is ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guity and doubt, and conſequently no ſuch plainneſſe and certainty as our Faith requireth; neither can that writing when it is wreſted againſt true meaning, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it ſelfe, or determine any contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie, that about the Letter or ſence thereof ſhall fortune to ariſe.</p>
            <p n="15">15 This rule then muſt be a liuing <pb n="25" facs="tcp:15185:15"/> rule, able to expound it ſelfe, and vnfold ſuch doubts which in matters of Faith ſhall fall out. And this I eaſily belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; for my owne reaſon doth dictate, that Almighty God would not vnder paine of Hell, binde all men to beleeue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and with a Diuine infallible be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, and leaue no rule, no meane, no ground open to euery one, and in it ſelfe infallible to eſtabliſh his beliefe vpon, and reſolue the doubts thereto apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining.</p>
            <p n="16">16 This liuing Iudge can be no pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man, for warranty in ſuch we haue none; neither is there cauſe to expect more in one, then in another; moreouer that muſt needes dye and faile, and ſo the rule of ſaluation periſh, and then the world to be left without meanes of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe vnto Almighty God.</p>
            <p n="17">17 A temporall or ciuill Common-wealth it cannot be, for no one Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth or temporall Congregation hath any colour of Authority out of Heauen to chalenge that priuiledge; Againe, no one Common-wealth hath continued ſince Chriſt, but hath ſufferd Change in the whole forme, yea Religion and all, and there is no cauſe to aſcribe this ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15185:16"/> more to one Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth then to another. There remaineth only an Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munity, to wit, the Church of Chriſt whereupon Catholicks doe rely, and aſſigne for this rule, wherein (as I doe confidently beleeue) they are not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; whereunto I am induced by eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent reaſon, by manifeſt and apparant authority, &amp; continuance of experience. For the infallible Authority left in this Community, we haue the expreſſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Almighty God in many places of holy Scripture, for of this Church our moſt Bleſſed Sauiour ſaith,<note place="margin">St. Math. 16</note> 
               <hi>Portae inferi non praeualebunt aduerſus eam, The Gates of Hell ſhall not preuaile againſt it. Vitia</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Hierome) &amp; peccatum &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In St. Math 16.</hi> St. <hi>Amb.</hi> lib. de bono. mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis cap. <hi>12.</hi> Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. in An.</note>He meant by theſe Gates, the vices, ſinnes, and Doctrine of heretiques, and the ſame in effect ſay the reſt of the holy Fathers. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that, <hi>Eccleſia Dei viui eſt columna &amp; firmamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veritatis, quod manifeſtum eſt in Carne, iuſtificatum eſt in ſpiritu, apparuit Angelis, predicatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, creditum eſt in mundo, aſſumptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt in Gloria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.</note> The <hi>Church of the liuing God, the piller and ground of Truth, and manifeſtly it is a great Sacrament of piety, which was manifeſted in Fleſh, was iuſtified in Spirit, <pb n="27" facs="tcp:15185:16"/> appeared to Angels, hath bin preached to Gentiles, is beleeued in the world, is aſſumed in Glory. Quia ab illa</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> 1. Ti. 3.</note>(ſaith St.
<hi>Ambroſe) firmantur in veritate omnes credentes, For aſmuch as from the Church all true Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers are eſtabliſhed in the Truth. Ego vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſcum ſum</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour)<note place="margin">S. Math. 28.
<hi>vlt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>omnibus diebus vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad conſummatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeculi, I am with you all dayes, euen to the conſummation of the world. Qui</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Mat. 28.</note>(ſaith St. <hi>Hierome) vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad conſummationem mundi ſuam praeſentia pollicetur, &amp; illos oſtendit, ſemper eſſe victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros, &amp; ſe nunqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a credentibus eſſe receſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum: Who promiſeth his preſence vnto the end of the world, ſheweth that they ſhall euer liue, &amp; that himſelfe will neuer depart from the faithfull.</hi>
               <note place="margin">St. Ioh. 14.</note> And in another place he ſaith (I meane <hi>Chriſt</hi> our moſt bleſſed Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our)
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Chriſ. hom</hi> 74. in Ioh.</note>
               <hi>Ego rogabo Patre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. I will aske the Father and he will giue you another Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clete, the ſpirit of Truth, that he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine with you for euer;</hi> which could not be meant of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> only to whom it was ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">St. Ciprian lib. <hi>9.</hi> in
<hi>Ioh.</hi>
               </note> but of the ſucceeding Church whoſe perſon they beare, and was to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to the worlds end. <hi>Non pro eis ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go tantum</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour)
<note place="margin">St. Ioh. 17.</note>
               <hi>I doe not onely pray for them, (meaning his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) but for them alſo that by their word
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15185:17"/> ſhall beleeue in mee, that they all may be one, as (the Father) in mee, and I in thee, that they alſo in vs may bee one, as wee alſo are one.</hi> And herein all holy Fathers doe aſſent, and plainely thus vnderſtand it.</p>
            <p n="18">18 This promiſe of the holy Ghoſt, St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth plainely teſtifie to be fulfilled, when he ſaith thus;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtus aſcendens in altum, captiua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> duxit captiuitate, dedit do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na hominibus,</hi> Chriſt <hi>aſcending on high, hee led captiuity captiue, he gaue guifts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men:</hi> where after a few wordes he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>Ipſe dedit quoſdam quidem Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, &amp;c.</hi> he <hi>gaue ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and other ſome Euangeliſts, and other ſome Paſtors and Doctors, to the conſummation of the Saints, vnto the worke of the Miniſtry, vnto the edifying of the body of Chriſt, vntill wee meete all into the vnity of Faith, and knowledge of the Sonne of God, &amp;c.</hi> In theſe places it is euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly promiſed, the aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, the continuance of the Church, the infallibility of her Faith,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> the aſſured Doctrine of her Paſtors, and Teachers, to bring her Children in <hi>vnitatem Fidei,</hi> into the vnity of Faith. Wee haue like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in Scriptures expreſſe commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment giuen to theſe Paſtors that they<note place="margin">Act. 20.</note>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:15185:17"/> carefully attend vnto their Flocke, and that they are to render an accompt of their ſoules;<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.</note>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 33.</note> which will be required at their hands, if through their default they periſh. Wee on the contrary part haue the like commaund who are the Laity,<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Heb. 13.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>S. <hi>Math. 18.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>St. Auguſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> aduer. Ioui.</p>
                  <p>Idem Epiſt. ad Heliodox.</p>
                  <p>St. Cipri. de vnit. <hi>Eccle. Num. 3.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> to obey the Paſtors, to take direction, Doctrine, and inſtruction, from them, as appeareth in many places of Holy writ, and that vnder paine of eternall Damnation. Wherefore that Chriſtian who followeth the direction of this Church, and obeyeth her precepts, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filleth Gods Commaundements, and ſo conſequently cannot erre, nor the Church erre in that direction.</p>
            <p>For if the Church could erre in that Direction and Doctrine, then were wee bound by Gods Commaundement to imbrace error, and from hence one or two abſurdities muſt needes ariſe, to wit, either that by error and falſhood we might be ſaued, or elſe for obſeruing Gods Commaundements, we might be damned; both which are moſt haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and apparant blaſphemy.</p>
            <p n="19">19 When I had found that this Church had the infallible promiſe of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, for the integrity and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15185:18"/> of her Doctrine, for her continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance vnto the end, that to her Paſtors and Teachers was committed the care of Chriſt his Flocke, that the ſaid Flocke was ſtraightly commaunded to obey them as their Spirituall guides; that very affection wherewith they deſired to be of this Flocke, joyned mee to this Church, and ſubjected me to this gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, that feare I had of miſtaking the Truth, (ſo needfull for the health of my ſoule,) made me cleaue to the aſſurance of this Direction, where the Spirit of God is to be my direction and guide, and his lawfull Officers my inſtructors; Now remaineth onely for me to learne out, where this eminent Citty of God
<note place="margin">St. Math. 5.</note>(<hi>Super montem poſita, Placed or ſeated vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an Hill,</hi> and caſting foorth ſplendour,
<note place="margin">St. Luk. 1.</note>
               <hi>Ad dirigendos pedes in viam pacis, To direct our feete into the way of Peace,</hi>) was to be found; and ſurely this Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, which is not
<note place="margin">S. Math. 5.</note>
               <hi>Sub modio poſita ſed ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per candelabrum, Put or hidden vnder a Euſhell, but ſet vpon a Candleſticke, Vt iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat eis qui in domo ſient, To giue light to thoſe that are in the Houſe,</hi> was eaſie to be diſcerned, and ſo it muſt bee if the promiſes of God were true, or his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence <pb n="31" facs="tcp:15185:18"/> ſufficient for the ſauing of ſuch ſoules, learned and vnlearned, for whom hee ſhed his moſt precious Blood, and dyed.</p>
            <p n="20">20 The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſo cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated &amp; knowne to the whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world, carrieth onely the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of this Truth. It hath knowne continuance with ſucceſſion of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors from the beginning of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity vnto this day. It hath preſerued the holy Scriptures from corruption, and deliuered them to poſterity from hand to hand, from age to age, to theſe dayes wherein we liue.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>St. Vincent</hi> Lyrinenſ. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha. haereſes.</note> It hath conſent &amp; vnity of Doctrine through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole world, &amp; the ſame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued throughout all Ages, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the oppoſition of Heriſie and infidelity, wherewith it hath continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally bin exerciſed. It hath preuailed againſt all Sects and Hereſies whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and beate them downe as they ſprung vp, different each from other (like vnto the prodigious heads of <hi>Hydra</hi>) at all times. It hath teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Miracles,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Beda</hi> lib. de <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> hiſt.</note> whereby the better to confirme her Doctrine, recorded by <pb n="32" facs="tcp:15185:19"/> moſt venerable Fathers, and approued Hiſtories, and annuals of all Ages. It hath Sanctity and Innocency of life and Doctrine, now ſealed and crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the blood of the moſt glorious Saincts and Martyrs of Heauen, and ſuch as our aduerſaries cannot deny to be ſuch. It hath the conſent of all generall and prouinciall Counſels, that haue euer bin lawfully gathered, and approoued in all partes of the world.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it hath Vniuerſality, true Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, Sacrifice, and all what euer markes the holy Fathers doe point our the true Church of Chriſt: by euery of theſe ſeuerall ſignes moſt eaſie to be proued, and in truth are manifeſt to him who will but peruſe the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Hiſtories of Times and Ages,<note place="margin">Euſeb. Zohomen. Dorethe. de hiſt. enl-</note> which my ſelfe by examining finding to be moſt true, cannot doubt of.</p>
            <p n="21">21 Finally if this be not it, on earth there is no true Church,<note place="margin">St. Chriſ. in Hom. quada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad populam Antioch.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt hath deceiued vs, the Apoſtles deluded vs, the Fathers wronged vs, and the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God haue failed.</hi> For it is moſt manifeſt, that no Congregation, no <pb n="33" facs="tcp:15185:19"/> Society, no Sect, no Doctrine, hath continued from Chriſt downeward vnder the ſucceſſion of Paſtors with one and the ſame Sacraments, vnder one forme of Gouernment, but onely this. And albeit ſome Sect hath for the time ſeemed powerfull, as the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, Pelagians, Donatiſts, and many others, yet were they no ſooner ſprouted vp, but they were ſeuered into innumerable diuerſities among themſelues, and at warres, yea, deadly fewd one againſt the other, and it is not vnknowne vnto your good ſelfe, but that <hi>Regnum in ſe diuiſum</hi> muſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,<note place="margin">S. Math. 12</note> if we may beleeue our moſt Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and moſt mercifull Redeemer, and ſo did they euery one in their turnes, inſomuch that the memory of them had not remained, if that Catholicke Fathers in Confutations written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them had not recorded their Errors, and preſerued the infamous memory of the Authors.</p>
            <p n="22">22 And what we doe finde true of all former Sectaries,<note place="margin">Luther in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad Iohan Heruag.</note> is notorious in
<hi>Martin Luther</hi> and his complyces, for their differences &amp; implacable hatred, <pb n="34" facs="tcp:15185:20"/> each againſt other,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tiſpogra. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. Zuingl. vbi ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pra.</hi> See a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Doctor
<hi>Stapleton</hi> called a diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>courſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Proteſt. printed at <hi>Louan.</hi> 12. of Nouember 1564.</note> is at large diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in their owne Writings, to bee found in almoſt euery Booke-ſellers ſhop. Inſomuch as ſince <hi>Luther</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his progeny, within one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, there are recorded more ſeuerall Sects, (I may truely ſay He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies) and more nouell opinions, hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and brought into the world, by their abortiue meanes, then in 1400. and odde yeares before. And com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon experience ſheweth, that euery man being his owne caruer and Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, ſhapeth vnto himſelfe a Faith out of his owne Braines.</p>
            <p n="23">23 And thus (good Sir) I not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to doe for the reaſons aboue mentioned, and for the danger it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth, had none other hope to ſaue my ſoule, but by committing my ſelfe to that guidance, where ſo many aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured promiſes of Gods aſſiſtance doe both inuite and warrant me, and ſo many infallible teſtimonies of his performance. encourage mee to the ſame.</p>
            <p n="24">24 Thus much (Sir) I haue deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, and theſe reaſons I haue allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <pb n="35" facs="tcp:15185:20"/> for the better approbation of my motiues, and thus much I haue ſet downe, to the end you might vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that I haue not done any thing which doth ſauour either of temerity or paſſion, but meerely out of true zeale, and an earneſt deſire I haue to let you ſee how ſollicitous I am to ſaue my ſoule, which (how ſinfull ſo euer it is) it hath pleaſed Chriſt our louing Sauiour to redeeme, by the purchaſe hee made, disburſing his owne moſt precious Blood. Nor doe I in this ſtand vpon mine owne opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but vpon the Iudgement and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the whole Church of Chriſt; neither haue I done this to any other purpoſe, but meerely and purely to giue your importunity content.</p>
            <p n="25">25 Theſe thinges I haue (I ſay) deliuered, and vnto them will I (God willing) adhaere, vntill ſuch time as better reaſon ſhall be giuen me. In the interim, I craue nothing but your Bleſſing and fauour: if you be pleaſed ſtill to caſt mee off, Gods will bee done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prouidentia Diuina haereditas mea: <pb n="36" facs="tcp:15185:21"/> I muſt take the Diuine prouidence to bee mine Inheritance,</hi> and then I ſhall haue iuſt cauſe to ſay, with that Bleſſed man Saint
<hi>Francis,</hi> who when his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had caſt him off for his ſtrictneſſe and auſterity of life, hee departed from his Fathers preſence, reioycing, and ſinging, <hi>Pater noſter qui es in Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> ſo may I ſay, <hi>Pater noſter qui es in Coelis,</hi> for vpon earth I haue not the comfort of a Father. Wherefore that comfortable ſaying of the Kingly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet can neuer depart from my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, <hi>viz. Quoviam pater meus &amp; mater mea dere deliquerunt me, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus antem aſſumpſit me, Becauſe my Father and my Mother haue forſaken me, but our Lord hath taken mee,</hi> and the comfort hereof ſhall be alwayes ready to accompany me.</p>
            <p n="26">26 Before I was a Catholicke, my exorbitant and irregular life much afflicted you, and now ſince I haue amended that fault, through the grace of God, and the helpe of the ſeauen <hi>Golden Candleſtickes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ap. 1.</note> ſpoken of in the
<hi>Apocalips,</hi> which are the ſeauen Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of God, which the holy Church <pb n="37" facs="tcp:15185:21"/> doth holde to bee the ſeauen Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, all which doe promiſe grace <hi>Ex opere operato,</hi> which I haue ſucked from the charitable breaſts of our moſt holy: Mother this Catholicke Church. You haue (Sir) little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to let that Religion, which reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med me from Vice, and hath beene the motiue to my amendment, adde matter to your greater affliction. Doe you deſire that I ſhould haue Saluation? then deny mee not that Faith which hath more then a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall aſſurance of Heauens happineſſe.</p>
            <p n="27">27 <hi>Out of the Catholicke Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tract. in col. cum Eremito</note> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine) a man may haue all thinges excepting Saluation, hee may haue Orders; hee may haue Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments; hee may ſing Alleluia; hee may anſwere Amen; hee may haue the Euangeliſts; he may haue and Preach in the Name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the Holy Ghoſt, but hee can by no meanes obtaine Saluation.</hi> Thus wrote and taught Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine.</hi> And ſeeing I haue ſome of his workes by me, I will alledge you one or two places more to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <pb n="38" facs="tcp:15185:22"/> wee haue in hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that I may omit</hi> (ſaith hee)<note place="margin">lib. cont. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. Fund. cap. 4.</note> 
               <hi>this Wiſedome which I deny to bee in the Catholicke Church, there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other thinges which doe moſt Iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly retaine, and holde mee within he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bounds and vnity: there doth holde me the conſent of People, and Nations the Authority which bad her begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by Miracles, nouriſhed by Hope, augmented by Charity, confirmed by Antiquity; There doth holde me the ſucceſſion of Biſhops</hi> (that is of Popes)
<hi>vntill this preſent Day, from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Seate of Saint</hi> Peter, <hi>to whome our Lord committed the feeding of his Sheepe, (after his Reſurrection) to the Epiſcopall Dignity of this preſent biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And laſtly, this very name Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, holdeth and detaineth mee in the vnity of thee Church, which Name, this Church, hath alwayes, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe among ſo many different Sects and Hereſies, in ſuch ſort obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that although all Heretiques doe deſire to bee called Catholickes, yet, if a Stranger (I meane a Iew, Turke, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15185:22"/> or one who is not a Chriſtian) ſhould demaund where is the Aſſembly of the Catholicke Church, there is no Heretique, who careth to aſſigne his Temple or his houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which may very aptly bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that worthy ſaying of Saint
<hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian, O beatam Eccleſiam noſtram, quam ſic honor diuinae dignitatis illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, quam temporibus noſtris glorioſus, Martyrum ſanguis illuſtrat, erat ante, in operibus fratrum candida, nunc facta eſt in Martyrum cruore purpurea, flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus eius nec Lilia, nec Roſae deſunt;</hi> That is, <hi>O happy is our Church, whome the honour of Gods Grace doth ſo ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, whome in our dayes the Glorious blood of Martyrs doth glorifie, ſhee was in the workes of our Brethren white be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but now ſhee is become in the blood of Martyrs of Purple colour, neither are Lillies nor Roſes wanting to her Flowers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="28">28 Thus wrote Saint <hi>Ciprian,</hi> rrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Church and of the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution thereof in <hi>Africa:</hi> Innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble other places of holy Fathers could I alleadge for this purpoſe, but I holde
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15185:23"/> it not needfull. I will heere end, for feare I labouring to giue content in Writing vnto you, might diſcontent you more by my perplexity, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauouring to auoyde one miſchiefe might happely fall into another, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the olde Prouerbe, <hi>Incidit in Scytham cupiens vitare Charibilem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="29">29 I therefore humbly craue your pardon to end, and withall intreating you no further to taxe me, then I ſhall be ready at all times,
<hi>Dum ſpiritus hos alit artus</hi> to continue.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Lodging indurance,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>this</hi> 15. <hi>day of Auguſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the</hi>
46.<hi>th Weeke of my Impriſonment,</hi> 1614.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your moſt dutifull Sonne, <hi>N. N.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15185:23"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15185:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15185:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
